Finding Aid for the Nancy Hendrix Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Nancy Hendrix Collection
2003
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0206
.42 linear feet
The Nancy Hendrix collection consists of one box, or .21 linear feet, of photocopied documents. Ms. Hendrix, a Vanderbilt alumnus (Masters Degrees 1967 and 1973; PhD 1974), was active in the establishment and development of the Nashville women’s movement in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
Topics covered in the collection include articles and clipping on the national women’s movement as well as other socio-political issues of the time period including southern history issues and the Vietnam War. Of particular interest in this collection is a series of papers published under the Southern Students Organizing Committee (SSOC) umbrella. Titles include “The New Nonviolience,” “Deliberate Depopulation of Whole Areas: A Protest,” and “Contemporary Forms of Imperialism.”
- Index:
  - The folder contains materials relating to Nashville Women’s Liberation Group (NWLG) and other socio-political activities. (Folder 1)
    - Meeting announcement and directions for Nashville Women’s Liberation Group, March 17, 1969 (Folder 1)
    - Petition to the Nashville Tennessean, undated (Folder 1)
    - Flyer for Spring Peace Offensive, April and May 1971 (Folder 1)
    - Response sheet for NWLG (Folder 1)
    - List of women involved in NWLG, undated (Folder 1)
    - Essay entitled “Female Liberation as the Basis for Social Revolution,” by Roxanne Dunbar, undated (Folder 1)
    - Women’s Network newsletter, Vol. I, No. 2, November 1976 (Folder 1)
    - Promotional flyer for National Council of Negro Women, Inc.’s Black Women’s Unity Drive, c. early 1970s (Folder 1)
    - Copies of index cards with names and addresses of NWLG participants (7 pages) (Folder 1)
  - Misc. clippings including coverage of the August 26, 1970 women’s movement nationwide strike and demonstration (Folder 2)
    - “U.S. Feminists Witches, Says Czech Paper,” from The Nashville Tennessean, August 24, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “Lib Woes Outweigh Good, Panel Told” from The Nashville Tennessean, Sept. 10, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - Photo with cutline titled “Contradiction of Terms,” from The Nashville Tennessean, August 27, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “Women Find Men’s Side Pays Price” from The Nashville Tennessean, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - Photo with cutline, ‘Support Women’s Lib, August 28, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - Resolution signed by Stephen Cobb, President of the Davidson County Young Democratic Club (Folder 2)
    - “Women Set to Strike Wednesday,” dateline New York, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “N. O. Men Have Come a Long Way, Baby,” dateline New Orleans, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Women’s Lib – To Be or Not To Be,” The Nashville Tennessean, August 28, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “China’s Liberated Women Aren’t Quite Equal,” The Nashville Tennessean, Feb. 20, 1972, by Caroline Benn (Folder 2)
    - Photo with cutline, “Welcome Sign to Liberation” date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “It Was a March for Liberation,” by Louise Cook, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Women’s Equal Job Guide Issued,” by Frances Lewine, The Nashville Tennessean, June 10, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “UT Coed Group Rebels Against Dorm Rules,” The Nashville Tennessean, April 30, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “B & PW Club Plans Discussion,” date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “B & PW Club Has Picnic,” date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Strong Female Voice Urged,” The Nashville Tennessean, August 11, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “House Passes Women’s Rights Proposal,” dateline Washington, DC, published in The Nashville Tennessean, August 11, 1970 (Folder 2)
    - “Guess Who Came to Dinner?” by Elaine Shannon, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Navy Woman Makes Waves Over Ouster,” dateline Pensacola, FL, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Senator Strikes Women’s Movement,” dateline Washington, DC, date unknown (Folder 2)
    - “Women’s Liberation is ‘Phony,’” editorial letter by Barbara Hysler, likely published in either The Nashville Tennessean or Nashville Banner, undated (Folder 2)
    - “Women’s Lib, and More,” date unknown (Folder 2)
    - Short history of the Nashville Women’s Center with annual expense breakdown (Folder 2)
    - Drawing and list of names and phone numbers in Nashville community (Folder 2)
    - “Mother, Volunteer Turns Minister,” The Nashville Tennessean, March 19, 1971 (Folder 2)
    - Draft of petition to the Nashville Tennessean, date unknown (Folder 2)
  - Items related to the Southern Female Liberation meeting, May 8-10, 1970 (Folder 3)
    - Flyer/registration form for Southern Female Liberation meeting (Folder 3)
    - List of attendees at the Southern Female Liberation meeting (Folder 3)
  - Misc. documents relating to the women’s movement in Nashville in the early 1970s (Folder 4)
    - Storyboard for proposed film, “Women and Men,” undated (Folder 4)
    - Synopsis for proposed film, “Women and Men,” undated (Folder 4)
    - Meeting minutes from Dec. 15 [1971] Nashville Women’s Coalition (Folder 4)
    - Calendar of Events/Newsletter from Nashville Women’s Coalition, July 1972 (Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet on prostitution, spousal abuse and other current women’s issues, undated, published by Nashville Women’s Center and Rape Prevention and Crisis Center (Folder 4)
    - Newsletter and Calendar of Events from Nashville Women’s Center (Folder 4)
    - January 1974 (Folder 4)
    - Nashville Women’s Coalition newsletter, May 1974 (Folder 4)
    - Nashville Women’s Coalition meeting announcement, June 7, 1972 (Folder 4)
    - Nashville Women’s Coalition newsletter, March 1972 (Folder 4)
    - Flyer, opening of Nashville Women’s Center, Feb. 5, [1972] (Folder 4)
  - Reference photocopies of images from Title IX demonstration staged at (Folder 5)
    - Austin Peay University, Clarksville, TN (Folder 5)
  - Southern Student Organizing Committee Publications (Folder 6)
    - Issue of Phoenix, Vol. 1, No. 5, a publication of the SSOC, [late 1968 or early 1969] (Folder 6)
    - Issue of Phoenix, Vol. 1, No. 6, March 1969 (Folder 6)
  - This folder includes miscellaneous correspondence, flyers, articles and SSOC reprints covering a wide range of socio-political issues of the 1960s and early 1970s. (Folder 7)
    - Letter dated March 23, 1969 to accompany bibliography on southern history (Folder 7)
    - Article titled “The New Nonviolence,” by Dave Dellinger, undated (Folder 7)
    - Article titled “Deliberate Depopulation of Whole Areas: A Protest,” by Albert Solnit, 1966 (2 copies) (Folder 7)
    - Excerpt, “Jefferson and Radicalism,” by Straughton Lynd, undated (Folder 7)
    - Paper, “The Cybernation Revolution,” presented by Robert Theobald at an address delivered April 7, 1964 to the 52nd Annual Conference of the Council of the Southern Mountains (Folder 7)
    - Paper, “The Decay of American Cities – Alternative Habitation for Man,” presented by Percival Goodman at a Conference on National Priorities Problem at Columbia University, Sept. 30 – October 1, 1966 (Folder 7)
    - Paper, “Student and Labor,” by Al Habor, undated (Folder 7)
    - Paper, “Contemporary Forms of Imperialism” by Conor Cruise O’Brien, reprinted from Studies on the Left, Vol. 5, No. 4, Fall 1965 (Folder 7)
    - Letter from SSOC, dated July 16, 1968, includes press releases dated, June 26 & July 16, 1968 (Folder 7)
    - Bibliography on Southern History (Folder 7)
    - Flyer, “The War Is Not Over In Vietnam or At Home,” [c. 1967] (Folder 7)
    - Editorial reprinted from The New South Student on abolishing the draft, by David Nolan, undated (Folder 7)
    - Article, “Brief Analysis of ‘Civil Rights’ Act of 1968 (H.R. 2516)” by William Higgs and Guy Smythe, undated (Folder 7)
    - Reprint, “A Threat to One…” by Anne Braden, undated (Folder 7)
    - Article from The Southern Patriot, “The White Poor – Only a Pawn in the Game” by Bob Analavage, January 1968 (Folder 7)
    - Editorial from The Movement titled “Where We’re At,” undated (Folder 7)
    - Article from The Movement titled “America, America…” [c. 1968] by Julius Lester (Folder 7)
    - Liberation newsletter, April 1967 (Folder 7)
    - I. F. Stone’s Weekly newsletter, Vol. XVI, No. 10, May 13, 1968 (Folder 7)
    - Article, “Political Programme of the South Vietnam National Front for Liberation” (Folder 7)
    - SSOC newsletter, September 18, 1968 (Folder 7)
    - Agenda for Conference on Radical Southern History, April 18 – 20, 1969, Emory University, Atlanta, GA (Folder 7)
    - Flyer, Agrarian Work Project, undated (Folder 7)
    - Conference for Movement in the South, June 5-8, Edwards, MS (Folder 7)
  - Article, “Girl Editor: Force to be Reckoned With” by Frank Ritter, The Nashville Tennessean, October 5, 1969. Feature story about Joanne Cooke, editor of “motive” magazine. (Folder 8)
  - Booklet, “No More Fun & Games,” by Roxanne Dunbar, August 1971 (Folder 9)